Welcome back to part two of the
subquery instructional videos.
The purpose of the second video
is to provide additional practice
opportunities and also to
introduce the substring function.
These videos, I try to keep them
a little bit shorter in length.
The challenge is topics like
subqueries, I hate to shorten because
the topic is important and I know
some of you struggle a little
bit more with subqueries than joins
although that's not always the
case but here's a blue triad number
three display the description
of activities that have fees paid
so these are fees paid not listed
price or list price of more than
20. So go ahead and pause the
video and try this one and again
you'll need the database diagram
to be able to figure out which
table or tables you'll need. In this
case, it provides the two tables,
student activity and activity.
All right, so here's the answer
to this particular question.
We asked the two questions, do
we need output from one table?
So here's the solution to
this particular problem, we do
satisfy the two questions of
doing a subquery for this class.
Is the output from one table? And
the answer to this is yes, the
activity table. And do we need
information from another table? The
answer to that is also yes. So
we write the subquery is select
description from activity, where
activity ID in, and then you know the
subquery will link the primary
foreign key so activity ID in select
activity ID from the student
activity table and I'll start to
get in this notion are we there
yet and by there yet I mean do we
have the information on the student
activity table is this the final
table if the answer is yes we
just use the predicate logic fee
paid greater than 20. If the answer
is no and we need to go to another
table that's where we would
indicate the where statement here
and then do a primary foreign key
link whatever that might be and
then start another subquery. So
we'll get to that in just a moment.
And then here's another
one, blue triad number four.
Display the activity ID for
fees paid greater than five
dollars. Remember you can use
columns and literal values.
Greater than five dollars more
than the minimum activity fee.
Don't include duplicate output. So go
ahead and pause the screen here. And
here is the solution to
blue triad number four.
It says don't include duplicate
output. In this case, I would
recommend just indicating select
distinct. You could run it to see if
by chance it does have duplicate
output, but when in doubt, you could
include with the select distinct
activity ID. This is all from
one table, so from student activity
where fee paid is greater than,
and then select, and here we
just have a simple formula,
the minimum fee paid plus
$5, otherwise it's just a
minimum, and then that comes
from the student activity table.
So that would be the solution
to BlueTriot number four.
And now this is a short commercial
break. It separates completely
from the topic of subqueries, but
we try to add new information either
through the labs or through the
discussions, the instructional
videos, or a combination of both. A
substring is used when you need to
gather data out of a larger set of
data. So maybe within a term or a
column, you just need part of that
column. In this particular case,
there are three arguments to the
substring. And part of studying for
the exam, including the date functions,
these date functions typically
have a number of what are called
arguments to the function. And
a substring is just like that.
It has three arguments. The first
thing is what column or literal value
you're interested in getting part
of. And then the first one indicates
the starting point. In a SQL
server with substring, the starting
point one would be the letter L.
It doesn't start at zero, it'll
start at one. And then the second
argument is how many characters do
you want to include? So in this case,
we want a substring of last name,
starting with their first letter
and getting three. So effectively,
this would get the first three letters
of somebody last name. M-I-L for
Mills, H-I-N for Hines, and that's
what the substring would do. You
could also use substring, for
instance, for a phone number. So if
you had a phone number, 888-123-4567,
you could do a substring, the phone
number, 1,3, and what would that
give you? That would give you the
area code. So if you just wanted
the area code, you would do something
similar. But that's substring.
And now we talk a little
about three table subquery. I
mentioned in the first subquery
that we did or subquery
earlier that you start to ask
the question, are we there
yet? So in this particular
case, here is the question.
Display the first three letters
of the student's last name. So
that's the easy little substring
right there. And then it's saying last
name that are associated with the
activity description basketball.
So if we go to activities, we
have student activity. There's no
description there. So we do
have activity, which does have
description. And in this case, it
represents that are we there yet. So
our first where statement would
be student ID to student ID to the
student activity table. And then
our next where statement instead
of predicate logic would be
connecting student activity to the
activity table. And you can go on
and on with this forever and ever.
Let me pull over SQL Server and I
will show you an example of this.
I hope I have the question here.
So we would say select the first
three letters of their last
name and we'll start with 1 then
and then 3 as first three and
this is from the student table and
then we get and then we get to
the where and the link between
the student table and the student
is a student activity table is
student ID so we would say where
student ID this is the primary
key in select you know it's going to be
here because it's the link student ID
and this is from student
underscore activity table.
Now, if we were there yet,
and I'm looking at the student
activity table, and we could
include some, and then an
and to keep going, but in
this case, if we needed fee
paid or start date or end
date, we could end right here,
but we don't. We need the
description, and so because of that,
we just go to our where clause,
And instead of having predicate
logic in the traditional sense,
you know, where last name equals
to Heinz, we'll use that
predicate logic to create another
subquery within a query. And in
that case, it would be activity ID.
And then we'll link that to,
excuse me, select activity ID from
the activity table.
Now the question again, kind of like
Bart Simpson has a video where he's
traveling somewhere. He's like, are
we there yet? Are we there yet? So
in this case, the same thing. Are
we there yet? In this case, we are.
So the where would be
where description is equal
to, and I have no idea
what our description was,
basketball.
And then in this case, we'll
need to have two more parentheses
at the end instead of one
because we have a three-table
subquery. It works similar to a
join, number of tables minus one.
And then we can close this
off. And let's run this code.
It's showing that I have
some error messages.
What is math about? Oh, excuse me.
Activity ID.
I was thinking, I guess,
of the table. So again,
primary, foreign, link. That's
where it was an easy fix.
And so here we have the first three
that are associated with basketball.
Now, how it's running, it's
going to take this information,
because it is a self-contained
subquery, so it's going to plop
one back, so this would be in
one, and then, of course, here,
it will get the information with
one, and then send that to the
outer query, and that is how
that three-table subquery goes.
and here's just an example
of that three table
subquery that we just did
you can pause the screen
if you want to take a
longer look at the code
this will be our last blue try it
write an SQL query that shows the
risk and list price of activities
that the student with the last name
Heinz participates in and this one we
don't give you the different tables
that are needed you can grab that
information from your sheet you
can also pause the video and just as
a reminder with blue try it we just
hope that you follow along and
participate in as many of the coding
activities as you can but if you
happen to miss one by all means it's
fine we just want to know that you
are primarily participating and in
this case we needed three tables
we have the activity table and the
output is from just the activity
table. That would be one rule. And
then we need information from another
table. In this case, we need our
information from the student table,
but we need to go via the student
activity table. If we try to cut
the corner, the code will run if we
can figure out some kind of link.
But in that case, we're not going to
get the results that we hope for.
And then we'll finish up today with
problematic null values.
List the last name in the
students, list the last
name of students that have
a locker in building B.
So I'm going to type this code.
Once we have the code copied
over, and if you would go
ahead and you can pause the
video and copy that code over,
select last name from student
where student ID in, we're used
to using in, and then in the
inner query select student ID
from gym locker where locker
location is equal to B. So
this is providing us the last
name of those who have an ID in
building B. So these are the
people that are in building B.
Let's take a look if we want to see who
is not in building B and run this code.
Wait a minute. Nobody is not in
building B suggesting that they're
all in building B. All of these
double negatives. Well in the
Ben-Gon book he has a great
section on why the not in can be
problematic and so if you read the
description what you would need to
do to solve this code is one
not use not in but the other one
would be also to say something like
and student id and we're talking
about student id of the gym
locker table so it's a foreign key
is not null.
And then it works just
fine. We have 34 students.
SQL Server, when doing this
subquery with not in, when it finds
a null value, it just shuts down.
It kind of short wires. It doesn't
really work. So this is the
workaround for that problematic not
in. So that concludes the second video
on subqueries. You'll now have a
chance later in the week to work on
the lab where it will include a
variety of questions to build off of
what you've done with joins last
week and then complementing your
skills with both type 1 and type 2
subqueries. So I hope this was helpful
for you. Best of luck in the lab.
That's where the real learning
takes place. I hope you have a great
day and we will see you next week.
Some people have bad hair day.
I'm having a bad helmet day.